<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A fruteful] and learned sermon preached in London; by a most worthy and faithful minister of Chrsit. For the great support and comfort of the people of God in evil times. Most learnedly opened, and prest from Psal. 97.11. Light is sown for the righteous. And farther shews, that if there be either justice in heaven, or fire in hell, persecutors shall never go unpunished</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2251A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825750</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40521)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1793:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A fruteful] and learned sermon preached in London; by a most worthy and faithful minister of Chrsit. For the great support and comfort of the people of God in evil times. Most learnedly opened, and prest from Psal. 97.11. Light is sown for the righteous. And farther shews, that if there be either justice in heaven, or fire in hell, persecutors shall never go unpunished</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint place and suggested expansion of title from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XCVII --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30137:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30137:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> And Learned SERMON Preached in LONDON; By a moſt Worthy and Faithful Miniſter of Chriſt. For the great Support and Comfort of the People of God in Evil Times. Moſt Learnedly opened, and preſt from <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 97. 11.</bibl>
                  <p>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</p>
               </q> And farther ſhews,
<q>
                  <p>That if there be either Juſtice in Heaven, or Fire in Hell, Perſecutors ſhall never go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:30137:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30137:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached One Faſt Day, <hi>LONDON.</hi> In the Year, One thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Seventy.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalm 97. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</bibl>
                  <p>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis Pſalm is very conſolota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, full of comfort for the Church of God: It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in an Elegant and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick ſtile. The Pſalm begins thus; <hi>The Lord Reigns let the Earth rejoyce.</hi> God hath a Superintendency over all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30137:3"/> humane affairs, he doth what he will: It is God that ſits Lord paramount, he hath a Negative Voice in the Counſel of men, <hi>The Lord Reigns,</hi> therefore, <hi>let the Earth rejoyce: Clouds and darkneſs are round about him: Righteouſneſs and Judgements are the habitation of his Throne.</hi> s if the Pſalmiſt had ſaid, The Providences of the great God, they are very dark and myſterious, we cannot ſee what he is doing, <hi>Clouds and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are round about him;</hi> but his wayes though they are dark, they are alwayes holy and wife, they are alwayes Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <hi>Righteouſneſs and Judgement are the habitation of his Throne.</hi> And ſo I proceed unto the words I have read, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given this ſhort preface, <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</hi> Let things go how they will, let Providence be never ſo dark and bloudy, here is the Saint comfort: God reigns, and he will have a care of his People, and will comfort them in the moſt diſmal times; <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous;</hi> which Tex
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30137:3"/> is like <hi>Iſraels Pillar of Fire</hi> in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs which did give them light. It is like the <hi>Mariners lanthorn,</hi> which gives light in a dark night: whether it be a dark night now, I leave it to you to judg: Here is the <hi>Marriners Lanthorn</hi> to give light to you in a dark night. <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous. Light,</hi> it is here a Metaphor, that is put here for comfort, becauſe Light, when it breaks out it gives abundance of comfort and chearing to the Spirit, as in Scripture Darkneſs is put for afflictions, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 2. <hi>A Day of Darkneſs and Gloomineſs;</hi> that is, a day of afflictions; why ſo, Light is put for comfort and for joy: <hi>Ester</hi> 8. 16. The <hi>Jews,</hi> they had light, and gladneſs and joy; ſo that here ſee by light in the Text, is meant comfort. <hi>Comfort is ſown for the Righteous;</hi> it is ſown, you know that ſowing prepares the earth for harveſt. <hi>Light is ſown:</hi> that is, joy, and peace, and comfort: it is preparing; the ſeed is in the ground: <hi>Light is ſown,</hi> and who is this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30137:4"/> ſeed of comfort ſown for? why in theſe words, <hi>ſor the Righteous;</hi> the wicked, they have nothing to do with comfort. Thoſe that do ſow in ſin, ſhall be ſure to reap in ſorrow. <hi>Job</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Even as I have ſeen thoſe that plough iniquity, and ſow wickedneſs, reap the ſame.</hi> Oh, they will have a ſad harveſt at laſt! but ſaith the Text, <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous,</hi> for the Godly, for thoſe in whoſe Spirit there is no guile. By righteous, I underſtand ſuch that are really holy upright Chriſtians: God eſteems them righteous, who have Chriſts merits imputed to them, and Chriſts Spirit imparted to them: the Righteous in the Text, they are ſuch as are upright, ſincerely holy, ſo it is in the next words, <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous, and gladneſs for the upright in heart.</hi> Thoſe are upright ones in whoſe Spirit there is no guile.</p>
            <p>In this Text then there are two things obſervable. <hi>First,</hi> Here is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing imployed, <hi>Light is ſown;</hi> it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30137:4"/> this, that the comforts of Gods people may be for a time, <hi>like the ſeed hid under ground;</hi> that is implyed clearly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Here is ſomething expreſt, <hi>Light is ſown:</hi> There is this expreſſion, though the comforts of Gods people are for a time hid, yet a ſeed of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſtill remains, <hi>Light is ſown for them.</hi> I ſhall begin with the firſt of theſe; that which is implyed in the Text: That the comforts of Gods people are often times hid, <hi>as the ſeed under ground.</hi> They have not that viſible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of their comforts; ſometimes they are hid, <hi>as the ſeed under ground.</hi> Now this I ſhall clear to you in a double ſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Their outward comforts may be hid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their Soul comforts, they may be hid for a time, <hi>as ſeed under ground:</hi> under the clodds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Saints outward comforts may be hid under ſickneſs, their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30137:5"/> may be hid under reſtraint, their names maybe hid under reproach; thus their outward comforts may be hid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The ſpiritual comforts of the Godly, they may be hid for a time, as the ſeed under the clodds: the Lord may conceal the evidence of his love; the Lord though he hath the heart of a Father, may have the look of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>Job</hi> 6. 4. <hi>The Arrows of the Almighty are within me, the poyſon whereof arinks up my ſpirit:</hi> he ſpeaks there of diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>the Arrows of the Almighty are within me. God hath wounded me.</hi> It e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to the <hi>Perſians,</hi> who in their War, did dip the point of their Arrows in Poyſon, to make them wound more mortally. So ſaith <hi>Job, The Lord hath ſhot his poyſonſome Arrows, and hath wounded me with it,</hi> the arrow of diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: thus you ſee the ſpiritual comforts of the Saints, they may be ſometimes hid from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But why does the Lord do thus?</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no wonder that the ſpiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of believers may be hid, <hi>as the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30137:5"/> ſeed under ground.</hi> No, comfort and they may be in diſſertion; for,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> The Saints comforts are no better than Chriſts comforts were; but Chriſts comforts were hid for a time, when he was in diſſertion, and cryed out, <hi>My God, my God;</hi> he was without comfort; and ſhall we wonder if God eclipſe our comfort, and we walk in the dark? did not Chriſt do ſo? our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are no better than Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts were.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Saints comforts are no better than their graces are, but the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Saints may ſometimes be hid, why then may not their comforts? their graces we ſee are often hid under much corruption, as Gold is hid under droſs; their faith is hid under much unbelief; their humility is hid under much pride; their love to Chriſt is hid under much love of the world: How did <hi>David</hi> here ſuffer an eclipſe? why now the Saints comforts are no better than their graces are; if their graces be hid, why may not their comforts be hid too?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:30137:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Saints Crown that is hid, their comforts are no better than their Crown is; but their Crown is hid, why may not their Comforts. A Crown is laid up; hid out of ſight, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>A Crown laid up for me:</hi> a Believers Crown, it is hid from the eyes of the world: the world ſees the Saints ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but doth not ſee their crown: and the Saints Crown is hid from their own eyes too for a while, 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 3. 2. It does not yet appear what we ſhall be, our happineſs that we hope for, it is hid out of ſight: why, if our crown be hid, why may not our comforts be hid? they are not better than our crown is? But you will ſay unto me, but why does the Lord thus hide the comforts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? does he intend to bury them? I anſwer, no: the Lord is all this while carrying on a deſigh of mercy and love to the Saints. Pray obſerve.</p>
            <p>1<hi>ſt. God</hi> hath a deſign in hiding their temporal comforts from them, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30137:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> God hath a deſign in the hiding the Saints ſpiritual comforts, and withdrawing them.</p>
            <p>1. The Lord hath a deſign in hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the temporal comforts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; God does it for this great end, that he may leſſen and unglew their hearts from the world. We oſt let the world have too great a ſhare in our love. It is a very hard thing to enjoy any tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mercy, and not make an Idol of it; and therefore the Lord in wiſdome and love, hides and withdraws thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the world from us. As, ſuppoſe that a husband were beyond the Sea, and he ſhould ſend his Wife a Jewel, and ſhe ſhould be ſo taken with the Jewel, as quite to forget her husband: was it not time for him to ſend home for the Jewel again, that ſhe might love him more: So it is here: the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richeth you with temporal mercies, health, and eſtate, ſends you theſe Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; you are apt to fall in love with theſe Jewels, and forget God that ſent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30137:7"/> them. It is time for God to call home for thoſe Jewels, that he might have more of your love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> God hath a deſign in hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and withdrawing the ſpiritual comforts of his People; their ſpiritual comforts, as,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Perhaps God ſees that they cannot bear comfort: comfort is not for all, it is like ſtrong Waters that break the Glaſs: Joys are ſtrong things, all cannot bear it, no more than a weak eye can bear the Sun. When <hi>Peter</hi> was upon the Mount of Transfiguration, the glory of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven began a little to ſhine in his eyes, he was tranſported, and ſaid, he knew not what thoſe ſugared joyes of Heaven were: they are ſo ſweet and raviſhing, that ſome have taſted of them and have died, they have not been able to bear them; therefore God hides and withdraws them: all cannot bear comfort.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:30137:7"/>
            <p>Secondly, God may hide thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comforts from Believers, for a time, that they may value them the more when they have them. Oh, brethren! Did we come by our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts eaſily, as Water at the ſtrſt pump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we ſhould begin to diſeſteem, and vilifie our comforts; that is our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Though <hi>Manna</hi> was Angels food, when it grew common, it was ſlighted, it was diſ-eſteemed: <hi>VVhat is this Manna, and who is this Moſes?</hi> they began to ſlight the <hi>Manna.</hi> When Pearls grew common at <hi>Rome,</hi> they ſlighted them, and wore them upon their ſhoes; ſo would we do with our ſpiritual comforts: therefore God, to inhaunce, and raiſe the price of our ſpiritual comforts; he does for a time ſuſpend them; hides them, as the ſeed under ground.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God may hide the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al comforts of his Children, for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; he will try their ingenuity, he will ſee what metal they are made of,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30137:8"/> whether they will ſerve him for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and not for comfort only. It is a harlots love, to love the Husbands mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and tokens more than his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Such as ſerve God onely for Comforts, they ſerve God more for his gifts than for himſelf. We do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſuch as will do nothing for us without a Fee; God likes not thoſe Chriſtians, who will ſerve him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when he fees, and bribes them with Comfort.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God hides his peoples ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comfort, that he may quicken the exerciſe of their Grace. Many times Grace is ſtrong, when Comforts are weak; Grace is at full-tide, when Comforts are but at a low ebb, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2. 4. <hi>I ſaid I was caſt out of thy ſight.</hi> There he had no comfort. <hi>Yet will I look again to thy holy Temple.</hi> There was a ſtrong Faith. Faith and Love, like two ſtarrs, ſhine brighteſt in the darkeſt night. In the night of diſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we are taken with Comfort, but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30137:8"/> God is more taken with the acting of our Grace. The truth of it is, when God ſometimes gives his people ſpiritual comfort, why then they are apt to be more remiſs in their walking, and they are not ſo quick and lively in duty as they were; juſt like Muſicians, as ſoon as you throw them down mony out of the window, they will leave off playing, you will hear no more Muſick. The Lord with-holds comforts from his people ſometimes, becauſe he loves to hear the muſick of their Graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> God hides the Spiritual comfort of the Saints for a time, that they may be more humble: there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the Saints are more apt to be proud of, than ſpiritual comforts, and enlargement; becauſe they look upon thoſe things as moſt excellent, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their hearts are apt to be lifted up. Now when God takes away thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and hides them, their hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be more humble. St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was, in being lifted up; when he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30137:9"/> had ſo many Viſions and Revelations. Therefore he had a Thorn in his fleſh to humble him. It was an humbling Thorne. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 12. <hi>Leſt that I ſhould be exalted above meaſure, thou hast given me a Thorn in the Eleſh.</hi> When Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have much joy in their Spirits, they need a thorn in the fleſh, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them. It is a very hard thing, to be high in joy, and to be low in humility. Oh, what corruption is there in mans heart? God cannot humble a Soul but it grows dejected; and God cannot comfort him, but he is ready to grow proud: and therefore he is forced ſometimes, to withdraw ſpiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, &amp; hide them, <hi>as ſeed under ground.</hi> God had rather you ſhould want com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, than that you ſhould be proud with your comforts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The Lord ſometimes hides the ſpiritual comforts of his people, and they walk in the dark, and ſee no light, that they may long the more to be in Heaven: then their comforts ſhall be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30137:9"/> in perfection, and ſhall never ceaſe; then the Saints they ſhall be upon the Mount of <hi>Viſion,</hi> ſeeing Gods glory e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſhall never complain more. <hi>My beloved hath with drawn himſelf.</hi> In Heaven, they ſhall have nothing but comfort then, becauſe they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but grace. The Saints they ſhall be for ever ſunning themſelves in the light of Gods countenance. Oh, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed time! Believers, they ſhall never have an angry word from God more; they ſhall never ſee a frown in his face more: the Sun-light of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour will be without clouds, and will never ſet; and therefore God lets our comforts be hid, <hi>as ſeed under ground;</hi> that we may long for a Spring-time of glory; when the flowers of ſpiritual Joy ſhall be fully ripe, and blown, we ſhall have comſort, and nothing but comfort. There ſhall be no more weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in Heaven, there ſhall be joy in Hell. Now to make ſome Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Then, if we ſee not Spiritual
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30137:10"/> joy riſing ſuddenly in our hearts, let us not wonder; you ſee God hath a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of love and mercy to his People, who hides Spiritual comforts! If God pleaſed, he could preſently let out the Sun-light of his face; he could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently give us joy; but he ſees it better ſometimes to be without it, than have it: the Sun dulls the fuel, and puts it out. The Sun-ſhine of comfort, makes the fervour of grace abate. Note there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, God hides the ſpiritual comforts of his Saints, <hi>like ſeed under ground:</hi> He is all this while carrying on a deſign of mercy, and love to them. To come to the next: this thing is implyed in the Text: Comfort may be hid as ſeed, <hi>as ſeed under clodds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I come to that which is expreſs'd here in the Text: Though the comforts of Believers are for a time hid out of ſight, <hi>as ſeed under ground:</hi> why, yet ſtill a ſeed of comfort remains for the godly: that is expreſs'd in the Text. Light, that is, Comfort is ſown for the righteous; though comfort is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30137:10"/> hid for a time, yet there is a ſeed of comfort ſtill remaining for all the righteous: this is, methinks, like a breſt of conſolation: do but lay your faith to this breſt, and you may ſuck out com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. This is the obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Doctrine is this;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That in the midſt of all tryals and diſcomforts of the godly, ſtill there is a ſeed of comfort left for them, <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</hi> Pſal. 18. 28. <hi>For thow wilt light my Candle:</hi> as if <hi>David</hi> had ſaid, though at preſent all my comforts they ſeem to be blown out: why, yet the Lord will light my Candle: <hi>Light is ſown for the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> Why, now you will ſay, Why will the Lord, in great trials of his people, preſerve a ſeed of comfort for them: <hi>Light is ſown for them.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, God does it for this end, that he may ſweeten Religion to them: if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing were to be ſeen but ſorrow and trouble; nothing but the dark ſide of the cloud, and there were no intervals, it would imbitter Religion: It would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30137:11"/> caſt a prejudice upon the ways of God; and therefore the Lord, that he may ſhew you the beauty and pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Religion, he does chequer his work, and preſerve ſome ſeeds of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the worſt of times: this ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens Religion, <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</hi> Now, to illuſtrate this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, to clear it to you, in caſe the Lord does preſerve alive ſeeds of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for his people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In their outward comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In their ſpiritual agony and diſſertion, God preſerves a ſeed of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for his people.</p>
            <p>1. In their outward trouble, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, in ſufferings: why, now God preſerves ſeeds of comfort; there are two ſeeds of comfort ſown for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, in time of Perſecution.</p>
            <p>1. The Promiſes are ſeeds of comfort in Perſecutions. There is no promiſe made to proſperity, but abundance of promiſes made to perſecution, &amp; theſe promiſes are ſeeds of comfort ſown for the Righteous. I will only inſtance in theſe four promiſes.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:30137:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> God hath promiſed, that he will moderate the ſury of his Enemies; he will, in the day of the Rough wind, ſtay the Eaſt wind: God will blunt the edge of their Razor, when their Spirits are ſharpened againſt the Righteous: God will blunt the edge, he will mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the ſtroke. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. 10. <hi>The remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of wrath thou ſhalt reſtrain.</hi> That promiſe is a ſeed of Comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Lord hath promiſed, that he will ſanctifie our Afflictions, and Perſecutions to us, they ſhall do us good. <hi>Jer.</hi> 24. 5. They ſhall be carried captive, but it is for their good, to make them holy, brightning their graces, fitting them for glory: fiery trials make good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Promiſe in Perſecution is this, that God will proportion his ſtrength to our tryals: and this promiſe is a ſeed of comfort. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 39. He is their ſtrength in the time of trouble: either God will lighten our burthens, or will ſtrengthen our faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Another promiſe is this, in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30137:12"/> Perſecution, that God will in his time open the door of deliverance for his People: when the Rod of the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor hath done its work, when it hath humbled, and purified the Saints, God he can ſoon throw away the Rod. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. <hi>He will with the temptation, make a way to eſcape.</hi> Never was <hi>Gold-ſmith</hi> more curious to obſerve when the Gold is thorough-refined, to take it out of the furnace, than God is to watch the firſt ſeaſon, when his People are fit for deliverance, then he will take his gold out of the furnace. Why, theſe promiſes are great ſeeds of comfort in an hour of Perſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As the promiſes are ſeeds of comforts, ſo Perſecution it ſelf does carry in it ſeeds of comfort for the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theſe two wayes. Perſecution it ſelf hath ſeeds of comfort in it, two wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Perſecution ripens the ſin of the Enemy, and as their ſin doth ripen, ſo the godlys deliverance does haſten.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:30137:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Perſecutions have ſeeds of comfort in them: as they are a means to diſtil comfort into the Soul: The Saints have joy out of ſorrow, as <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> had honey out of the Lion. <hi>John</hi> 16. 20. <hi>You ſhall be ſorrowful, but your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhall be turned into joy:</hi> by the very Perſecution, God will let in more joy into the Soul: <hi>your ſorrow,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>ſhall be turned into joy:</hi> here is water turned into wine. The Soul hath never ſo much of God, as in an hour of affliction: this made <hi>Paul</hi> to glory in tribulations, and as a Bird, to ſing in Winter. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 4. Thus, you ſee, the Saints very perſecutions do carry in them ſeeds of comfort for them. <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The inward Agony of the Soul, and diſſertion: ſtill God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a ſeed of comfort in the Soul: <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</hi> When God hides his face from his people, looks like an enemy, draws a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain between him and his people; why, yet all this while, in this agony,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30137:13"/> there is ſome ſeed of comfort left in the Soul. But you will ſay, what ſeeds are here? Theſe two.</p>
            <p>1. This is a ſeed of comfort in diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that God is ſtill a God in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, there is a ſeed of comfort. Though the Lord may forſake us in regard of Viſion, he will never forſake us in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Union. The Covenant rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Marriage relation ſtill holds, that is a ſeed of comfort. A Husband, he may be gone a long Voyage, he may be a thouſand Leagues off from his Wife; Oh, but ſtill the Marriage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation holds between them; God may be gone, diſſert the Soul, but ſtill the Marriage knot is bound, God is a God in Covenant. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 53. <hi>I will make an everlaſting Covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David.</hi> Beloved, Gods truth is the richeſt Jewel of his Crown, and he hath laid this Jewel to pawn, in the Covenant; he hath promiſed, he hath ſworn it, <hi>he will be our God eternally.</hi> Though it is true, we forſeit the mercy of the Covenant,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30137:13"/> yet God will not break the truth of the Covenant. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 28. <hi>My Covenant ſhall ſtand faſt.</hi> The earth does not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſtand faſt, that is ſhaken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, as in ſome Earth-quakes: Oh, but faith God, <hi>My Covenant ſhall ſtand faſt. Mat.</hi> 2. 16. The God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> faith, that he hates putting away. God that would not have other men put away their Wives, do you think he will divorce his own Spouſe? the Lord hates putting away. Here is ſeeds of comfort in diſſertion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In diſſertion, in a Spiritual Agony: why, now grace is a ſeed of comfort, the tree may be without bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and without fruit, but ſtill it is alive, there is ſap in the root of the tree; there may be vital ſap, and grace in the heart, though fruit of joy and aſſurance be not ſeen.</p>
            <p>But a diſſerted ſoul will ask me this queſtion, when grace appears now in an hour of diſſertion, to be a ſeed of Joy, and a ſeed of comfort? I anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:30137:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Soul mourns for Gods ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, that ſhews grace. It is a ſign love is in thy heart, elſe thou wouldeſt not Mourn for Gods abſence. When the Sun is gone, the dew falls; when God withdraws from the Soul, why then the dew of tears that drops from the eye, (<hi>David</hi> felt this mourning, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Gods abſence) that is a ſign of grace in the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When the Lord hath left thee in diſſertion, a Chriſtian hath quite loft his taſte to all worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, like one in a Fever, every thing taſtes bitter, he takes content in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſo long as he cannot enjoy God. As <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, I may elude to it, <hi>I went mourning without the Sun:</hi> ſo a poor diſſerted Chriſtian, I go mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and down without the Sun; God gives me ſome Star-light, ſome worldly comfort: what is all this? ſtill in a night of diſſertion. <hi>I went mourning without the Sun, I cannot ſee Chriſts face, the Son of Righteouſneſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30137:14"/> doth not ſbine.</hi> Is not this a ſeed of grace? the Soul hath loſt its taſte to all worldly comfort; he cannot taſte the ſweetneſs in Friends, and eſtate, as he could do. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 32. Saith <hi>Abſolon,</hi> Let <hi>me ſee the Kings face.</hi> Oh, nothing will ſatisfie a poor diſſerted Soul, but to ſee the King of Heavens face, to ſee Gods ſmiling countenance: why, this ſhewes, that the Soul is deeply in love with God, and ready to faint away for him; this grace is a ſeed of comfort, in an hour of diſſertion; thus you ſee <hi>light is ſown for the Righteous.</hi> Both outward troubles, perſecutions, inward agonies, diſſertions; thus you ſee, <hi>light is ſown for the Righteous:</hi> ſeeds of comfort is ſtill left in that Soul. Let me now come to make ſome Application; and the Lord give a bleſſing to it. Three ſeveral infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences I ſhall draw from this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>1. See then from hence, my Brethren, the ſuper-abundant goodneſs of the Lord to his people, in the midſt of all their ſorrow and ſufferings; ſtill he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a ſeed of comfort for them: <hi>light
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30137:15"/> is ſown for the Righteous.</hi> God does che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer his work with troubles; he does intermix comfort like a Limner, who mingles bright colours with dark ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows; I may elude to that Scripture, <hi>Zac.</hi> 14. 7. I do but elude to it. <hi>It ſhall not be day nor night.</hi> Neither day, nor night; the people of God, they have ſome afflictions, ſo that it is not day, yet they have ſome ſeed of comfort in their Souls, ſo that it is not night: <hi>light is ſown for them.</hi> The condition of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in this world is never ſo bad, but they may ſpie mercy in it, they may ſee ſome light, they may behold a <hi>Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow</hi> in the black cloud. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148. 7. <hi>Though I walk in the borders of trouble, thou wilt revive me. Joſeph</hi> was in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there, he was in affliction, but the Lord was with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> there was a ſeed of comfort. <hi>Paul</hi> had a thorn in the fleſh, there was his trouble, but God ſaid to him, <hi>My grace ſhall be ſufficient for thee;</hi> there was a ſeed of comfort. In the <hi>Ark,</hi> there was laid up the Rod, and <hi>Manna</hi> together; truly in this life, Gods people,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30137:15"/> Gods ſuffering people, with the Rod, taſte ſome <hi>Manna.</hi> Oh, the goodneſs of God, that never brings his people ſo low, but ſtill reſerves ſeeds of comfort for them, that they may not murm ure, but rather praiſe him in their worſt condition; that is the firſt inference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If it be Gods work, and his great deſign, to ſow ſeeds of comforts for the Righteous; than what will we think of thoſe, who are ſowing ſeeds of ſorrow for the Righeous? Surely theſe act directly againſt God, there is a woe belongs to them, that make the heart of the Righteous ſad, whom God will not have made ſad. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. 22. God is ſowing light for his people, and theſe men are laying ſnares for them: God is powering in Wine and Oyl in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his peoples wounds, and they powre in Vinegar: theſe act directly contrary to God, who ſtill would preſerve ſeeds of comfort for the Saints. We read in Scripture of Gods Bottle, &amp; of his Bag; of Gods Bottle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56. 8. and of his Bag, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 17. The Lord will put the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30137:16"/> tears of his Saints in his bottle, and he will ſeal up the ſins of the wicked in his bag: ſuch as afflict the righteous, they ſtrike at Chriſt through his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſides: let them take heed, God is making his Bow and Arrows ready to ſhoot. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 13. <hi>The Lord ordains his Arrows againſt the Perſecutors.</hi> Never did any perſecutor thrive on that trade, but were broken at laſt. <hi>Domanter,</hi> and others ran mad and poyſoned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeves. <hi>If there be either Juſtice in Heaven, or Fire in Hell, Perſecutors ſhall never go unpuniſhed.</hi> That is the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> See here the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the wicked and the godly. Oh, here is a great difference, the godly in all their ſorrows have ſeeds of comfort ſown for them. The wicked in all their comfort have ſeeds of ſorrow ſown for them: What are thoſe ſeeds of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that are ſown for the wicked? they are the threatnings of God. Here be ſeeds of ſorrow, ſo long as the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and thoſe ſeeds will come up, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 21. <hi>God ſhall wound the head of his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30137:16"/> enemies, and the hairy ſcalp of ſuch an one that goeth on in treſpaſſes.</hi> Why, this threatning is a ſeed of ſorrow, ſown for the wicked. Oh, it is a dreadful thing to be in the number of the wicked; to be of the Devils black-guard: the ſinner he lives every day in fear of arreſting; there remains for him, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftle, a fearful looking for a Judgment, and fiery indignation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 27. A wicked man, when he dies, he drops in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the grave, &amp; into Hell both at once. God is brewing for the finner a deadly cup; Oh, it will make him heart ſick. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57. 8. In the hand of the Lord, there is a cup, the wine is red, it is full of mixture; the dregs there of, the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the earth ſhall drink them out: this Wine is the wrath of God. It is burnt wine, and this cup of wine is full of mixture: what is that mixture in the cup? the worm of Conſcience, and the fire of Hell, here is a mixed cup, and the wicked ſhall be ever drinking of it: yea, the very dregs: God will never ſay to the damned in hell, <hi>Let this cup paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30137:17"/> from you:</hi> Methinks this might damp a ſinners mirth: there are ſeeds of ſorrows. All the threatnings of God ſown for the wicked. It was ſad news the Devil brought to <hi>Saul,</hi> oh, it muſt needs be bad news, where the Devil is the meſſenger. I <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. 19. Saith the Devil to <hi>Saul, Tomorrow thou ſhalt be with me.</hi> There are ſome ſinners in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that ſhall be with the Devil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to morrow. Here is a cooling Card for wicked men. There is ſeeds of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, threatnings of God ſown for the wicked; they will ſpring up in time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If there be ſeeds of light and comfort ſown for the Righteous; then when a child of God does not ſee the flower of comfort, let him rejoyce in the ſeed of grace; when he does not ſee the flower of comfort, yet let him rejoyce in the ſeed of grace; this ſeed will bring comfort in time.</p>
            <p>Now a child of God will make this objection. Alas! I could take comfort, if I culd find the ſeed of grace in my Soul: but I have ſuch a deal of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30137:17"/> that I fear, there are no ſeeds of grace left now. To this I anſwer. There may be ſeeds of corruption in the heart, where there are ſeeds of grace. The change that grace makes in the Soul, is a real change, but it is not perfect: Doth not <hi>Paul</hi> complain of <hi>a body of death, Rom.</hi> 7. 23. He who hath moſt faith, had need pray, <hi>Lord, help my unbelief.</hi> Alas, our grace in this life, will be mixed with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: our wheat is mingled with chaff: our ſtars with clouds. The beſt Saint alive, is like <hi>Jacob,</hi> who, though he prevailed with God, yet he went hault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away: what pride was there in Chriſts own Diſciples, when they were ſtriving which of them could be greateſt. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 24. Chriſtians look not for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection here; God ſees it is good that ſin ſhould be left in us a while, to keep our Souls humble. Gravel and dung may help to ballaſt the ſhip, that it overturns not. Oh! this dung of ſin ballaſteth a Soul, keeps it very low and humble: Say not therefore, thou haſt no ſeed of grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt ſeed of corruption. Let
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30137:18"/> me ask thee this queſtion; Doſt not thou mourn for thy ſin? Is not a proud, and a dead heart thy burthen? Are not thy eyes a ſpiritual Limbick, dropping holy tears for ſin? and doſt not thou prize Chriſt? couldſt not thou be willing to part with all, for the Pearl of price? and doſt not thou maintain a combat with thy corruption? why, that is a ſign there is life of grace, elſe no combat. Dead men do not fight: Grace is ſeen as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting ſin, as in overcoming it. Why then, Chriſtian, thou haſt the ſeed of grace in thy Soul, be thankful for this grace, though thou haſt not the ſeed flower of joy flouriſhing in thee. Why, look upon the Husbandman; when the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath ſown the ſeed in the Field, he takes comfort in that ſeed ſown, he knows there will be a crop e're long: So, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, if thou findeſt theſe ſeeds of grace ſown in thy heart, take comfort, there will be a Crop of joy ere long in thy Soul. That is the fourth inference.</p>
            <p>5<hi>th. Inference.</hi> If light and comfort be ſown for the Righteous; why then here
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30137:18"/> is comfort this day for the Church of God in <hi>England;</hi> the ſeed is in the ground, and deliverance in Gods due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhall ſpring up to the Church. Light is ſown; what if I ſhould ſay, <hi>Light is ſown for</hi> England: I would revive your ſpirits in time of ſadneſs and drooping. Let our faith get above our fear. <hi>Mica</hi> 7. 9. <hi>Rejoyce not against me, O mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: though I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me.</hi> It is the voice of the Church, Light is ſown for the pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and the Church of God. I conſeſs, things here amongſt us, as they have a ſad aſpect at this day, I would be ſenſible of our condition. If we are not ſenſible of Gods hand, we cannot be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under it. I would be ſenſible, gray hairs are here and there; ſad ſymptoms of Gods diſpleaſure are upon us: our ſins grow higher, our trading grows lower; our diviſions grow wider, and therefore our ſeats grow ſtronger. Oh! how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Judgments of God hath <hi>England</hi> felt of late years, for its ſins; and yet. we go on, as it were, in deſpight of Heaven:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30137:19"/> We do at this day hang out a flag of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt the God of Heaven: &amp; may we not yet fear, ſome other Judgments may yet enſue. Poor <hi>England,</hi> it is like the Ship in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> almoſt covered with waves. <hi>England</hi> lies a bleeding, with the wounds that her ſins hath given her; God grant it be not a ſickneſs unto death: yet, I ſay, in this day of Mourning, I would not have you mourn, as they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope. Theſe things may humble us, and ſet our eyes abroach with tears: yet mourn not, <hi>as them without hope. I would come as the Dove, with an Olive leaf of peace in my mouth, to you this day.</hi> My Text tells you, <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous.</hi> There is a little light, God knows, it is but very little light, we can ſcarce ſee it at the Key-hole; but there is ſome Light ſown for the Righteous. There is three ſeeds of comfort, for this poor, dying, ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> God hath a people in this Land that fears him, and are very dear to him: that is one ſeed of comfort; they are to him, as the apple of his eye;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30137:19"/> they are the glory of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 23. As they are called, they are Gods Jewels, and all the reſt of the world are but Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. God hath a people dear to him in <hi>England.</hi> The Lord would have ſpared <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> if there had been but ten Righteous Perſons in it: it is to be hoped, there are many tens in <hi>England.</hi> Were the godly removed, as it is the deſire of ſome, to give them their paſs to be gone; why, God would ſoon make quick work with the Nation: he would ſoon break up houſe in <hi>England.</hi> Were it not for the Elect, he would ſoon ſink Ship and State, but for ſome of the Elect Jewels in the Ship: but for their ſakes, the Lord may reprieve the Nation, and may adjourn its Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals a while longer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another ſeed of Comfort for the Land, is this, The mercies of God in Chriſt; that is a ſeed of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. The mercy of God in Chriſt. What cannot mercy do for a poor Nation? Mercy can throw forth a plank to us, when we are drowning. The Sun is not ſo full of light, as God is full of love.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30137:20"/> Mercy, it is that which pleaſeth God. <hi>Mica</hi> 7. 18. <hi>Mercy pleaſeth thee.</hi> Why may we not hope that the Lord will do that which is ſo pleaſing to him, that, which is his recreation, to ſhew mercy. Malice pleaſeth the Wicked, but Mercy pleaſeth God. Juſtice is called, <hi>Gods ſtrange work, Iſa.</hi> 28. 21. <hi>A strange work.</hi> As if the Lord were not uſed to it. We ſhall obſerve in the Scripture, when the Lord is going to ſhave off the pride of a people; he is ſaid to hire the very Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7. 20. As if he had none of his own, he was fain to hire one. When God executeth juſtice upon a people, he is ſaid to come forth from his place to puniſh. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 21. The <hi>Bee</hi> doth naturally give honey; it ſtings only when it is provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. God doth naturally ſhew mercy: Mercy, my brethren, it is Gods darling attribute, that he delights moſt of all to magnifie. Why, methinks this is a ſeed of comfort for <hi>England.</hi> Why may not mercy give the caſting voice, to ſave this Nation? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 9. <hi>In his love, and in his pity he redeemed them.</hi> In his love and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30137:20"/> Mercy does more overflow in God, than ſin can in us, or we could never be pardoned.</p>
            <p>Oh, but you will ſay, we are not a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are fit for mercy: what ſhould we do with mercy, that have ſo abuſed, and ſo provoked it? why, to this, I ſay, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath healing in its wings. It can as well give a Nation repentance, as deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance. It can as well prepare us for mercy, as beſtow mercy. Mercy hath healing in its wings: why, that is a ſeed of comfort.</p>
            <p>The third ſeed of comfort for the Land is this, That Spirit of Prayer, that is yet kept up among Gods people: Prayer uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in deliverance. It is the Midwife that helps to deliver the Church, when ſhe is in pangs. <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 32. <hi>whoſoever ſhill call upon the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> The ſparkling walls, were their ſpear walls: and the Bulwark of a Land is Prayer: Prayer it is a ſeed that is ſown in the ears of God. Nay, in the heart of God. Prayer commands God. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 11. <hi>Concerning the work of my hands command
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30137:21"/> ye me.</hi> That is, by Prayer. <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er held God, it held him faſt. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. 26. <hi>I will not let thee go, except thou bleſs me.</hi> I but pray obſerve obſerve, <hi>Moſes</hi> Prayer ſeems to have more force and power in it, than <hi>Jacobs</hi> Prayer had, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 10. Saith God to <hi>Moſes, Let me alone, that my wrath may wax hot againſt them. And Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſought the Lord, and the Lord repented of the evil.</hi> Pray obſerve, <hi>Jacobs</hi> Prayer prevailed with God, when God had a mind to ſhew mercy: But <hi>Moſes</hi> Prayer prevailed with God, when God was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; ſo that, to ſpeak with reverence, whether God be angry, or whether God be pleaſed; Prayer, why that prevails with him: this is a ſeed of comfort for this poor Nation. There are many, that every day beſiege Heaven with Prayer; ſends up whole volleys of ſighs and groans to Heaven. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 23. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaid, he would deſtroy them.</hi> Had not <hi>Moſes,</hi> his ſervant, ſtood in the breach, to turn away his wrath from them. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hath influence upon the Almighty. Prayer finds God free, but leaves him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30137:21"/> bound: eſpecially Chriſt praying our prayers over again; and ſprinkling them with his bloud, makes them go up, as ſweet incenſe to Heaven: ſo that theſe are ſeeds of comforts for this poor dying Nation. <hi>Light is ſown for England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bat here I muſt inſert a caution: and I beſeech you to obſerve. Though there be ſome light ſown for them, yet take this caution; Expect an hour of darkneſs. It is uſually dark before morning. Things are like to be worſe with us, before they are better: you know, the ſeed dies in the ground, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſprings up. Things ſeem to be in a dying condition; the ſeed is dying in the ground: e're light comes, expect ſome darkneſs.</p>
            <p>It is Gods uſual method, he uſhers in deliverance, by great afflictions: he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares for deliverance by afflictions: he brings his people into the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and then he ſpeaks comfortably unto them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 14. Shall I give you ſome Scripture inſtances? There will be ſome darkneſs before light do ſpring up: ſome Scripture
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30137:22"/> inſtances to clear it up. God gave <hi>David</hi> a promiſe of a Kingdom; <hi>David ſhall wear the Crown;</hi> I, but before that, <hi>David must fly for his life,</hi> he muſt be <hi>hunted as a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge upon the Mountains:</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, then he ſhall <hi>wear his Crown. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> he had the promiſe of a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Progeny, as the Stars of Heaven, but before that, his Wives womb muſt be barren. <hi>Moſes,</hi> he was to work delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he was to be their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Saviour; before his hand wrought any Miracles, his hand muſt be <hi>Leprous.</hi> Chriſt he was to come into the World; there was the great Light of the World: I, but before that Light came, it was an hour of darkneſs to the Church of God. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 2. <hi>Thoſe that dwell in the ſhadow of death, to them hath the Light ſhined.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Goſpel-deliverance, you muſt expect ſome ſore pangs, and the reaſon of it is this; here is the reaſon; Becauſe God hath a great deal of work yet to do; there is much rubbiſh to be removed, before Gods ſpiritual Temple will be built; ſins muſt be brought lower; Superſtition
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30137:22"/> muſt be purg'd away; the Devil muſt be caſt out and will not this think you, cauſe great commotion in the Church? and Convulſion fits, before light ſprings up: Therefore, look for an hour of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay to me, if it be ſo, then what ſhall we do in this hour of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? how ſhall we behave our ſelves, till this Light doth ſpring up to the Church? Let us do theſe three or four things, when it is an hour of darkneſs.</p>
            <p>1. Let us get into our Chambers, there our great work it lies, between God and our own ſouls: go into your Chambers: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 20. <hi>Come, my people, enter thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Chamber, hide thy ſelf.</hi> What Chamber, you will ſay, muſt we go into?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Let us go into the Chamber of our own hearts, by meditation, and by Self-examination. Let us ſee how the caſe ſtands between God and our own Souls: let us prove our ſelves, whether we are in the Faith: let us be clearing our eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces every day: let us bring our graces to the touch-ſtone: let us never leave, till
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30137:23"/> we have found out, we have a Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſt with God. When things are dark without, it is good that all ſhould be clear within: that is one Chamber: we ſhould go to our own hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us go into the Chamber of Divine promiſes, and, as it were, lock up our ſelves with God in theſe Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Oh, the ſweet promiſes that we ſhould now go unto, and fly unto as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; God hath promiſed, <hi>He will never leave us, nor forſake us.</hi> If you do not leave God, he will not leave you. God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>He will be our Sun and our ſhield, Pſal.</hi> 84. 11. In troubleſome times he will be our ſhield, to defend us: he will be our Sun, to enlighten us, and comfort us. Let us hide ourſelves, by Faith, in theſe Chambers: by the Promiſes. That is the firſt work.</p>
            <p>If an hour of Darkneſs be, go unto your Chambers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Having done this, Let us commit our ſelves to God, and truſt our ſelves upon his Providence <hi>Pſalm</hi> 45. 5. <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30137:23"/> thy way to the Lord. In the <hi>Hebrew</hi> it is, <hi>Root thy way upon the Lord.</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, let us not be too ſollicitous about iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues and events of things: caſt your bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then upon the Lord. So far as care is a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, take it upon your ſelves: but ſo far as care is a burthen, caſt it upon God.</p>
            <p>Again, having done this, got into our Chambers, and rooted our wayes upon the Lord; truſting the iſſues of things with him: why then, in this hour of darkneſs, oh, wait with patience, till Light ſprings up to the Church; that is the great work, that now God calls to his people for: wait with patience, do not murmur, but wait: do not wait through unbelief; do not fret through impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but wait till Light ſprings up. It ſhall ſpring up in Gods due ſeaſon: All the enemies of the Church ſhall not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Light ſpringing up.</p>
            <p>Deliverance is coming, when Gods time is come. We read, that when Chriſt was to riſe out of the Grave; though there were a ſtone upon the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30137:24"/> door of the Sepulchre, the Angel rowled away that ſtone, and Chriſt did ariſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly. This ſeems, methinks, to be the time of the Churches Burial, and there ſeems to be a ſtone rowling over the Grave: but when the time of her Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is come, God himſelf will rowl away the ſtone from the Sepulchre. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 8. It is ſpoken of Chriſt, <hi>Behold, he comes leaping upon the Mountains, skipping upon the Hills.</hi> My brethren, either Jeſus Chriſt will remove the Mountains, or he will come leaping over them: he will deliver his people; and till then, let us wait. And that we may get into a wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſture, conſider theſe two or three things, and ſo I have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Our betters have waited; the Patriarchs of old, they waited, till mercy and light did ſpring up. Why, you know <hi>Moſes</hi> he waited, and <hi>Abraham,</hi> he wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Jacob,</hi> he waited, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 18. Saith <hi>Jacob, I have waited for thy Salvation, O Lord.</hi> The people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they waited four hundred years for deliverance: and if they waited four hundred years, cannot we wait a few hours?</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:30137:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Wait till Light ſprings up for the Church: conſider, we have a full God to wait upon: a Beggar is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to wait at a rich mans door, there is ſomething ſtill coming.</p>
            <p>God hath treaſures of mercy lying by: he hath more bleſſings to give, than one; we have a full God to wait upon, and ſhall not we wait? he Lord is not a ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſountain, but he is a flowing fountain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The mercies we are in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of, they are worthy waiting for; the mercies we have prayed for, and are in expectation of, they are worthy wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for, to ſee the golden Fleet of Prayer coming home, with rich return; is not that worth waiting for?</p>
            <p>To ſee; the Lilly and the Roſe united; I mean, Truth and Peace. To ſee wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs diſcountenanced, and all its forces disbanded. To ſee the beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhining in our Chriſtal. To ſee Jeſus Chriſt riding in Triumph in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots of his Goſpel Adminiſtration. To ſee Righteouſueſs exalted, and, like the Wings of a Dove, covered with Silver.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:30137:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Wait till Light ſprings up to the Church; conſider this, the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Promiſes that are made to waiters, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 18. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that wait for him</hi> (A waiting condition is a bleſſed condition.) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. <hi>They ſhall not be aſhamed that wait for him.</hi> We account a mans Bond a very good Security: Thoſe promiſes they are Gods bonds, and they have a double Seal ſet to them; the oath of God, and the bloud of God: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us wait patiently; let us wait chearfully, till Light doth ſpring up, and flouriſh unto a Harveſt Deliverance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30137:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
